<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An edifieing wonder, of two children dyeing 100 yeares old or A short account of the last houres of Susanna Bickes (in the 14 yeare of her age) before her death. Septemb. 1. 1664. Also of Jacob Bickes her brother of 7. yeares old. Aug. 6. 1664.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3807A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832782</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2060:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An edifieing wonder, of two children dyeing 100 yeares old or A short account of the last houres of Susanna Bickes (in the 14 yeare of her age) before her death. Septemb. 1. 1664. Also of Jacob Bickes her brother of 7. yeares old. Aug. 6. 1664.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Mostly in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages cropped and stained with print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bicks, Susannah, 1650-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bicks, Jacob, 1657-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EDIFIEING WONDER, OF Two children dyeing 100 yeares old OR A SHORT ACCOUNT OF THE LAST HOURES OF SUSANNA BICKES, (In the 14 yeare of her age) before her death. Septemb. 1. 1664. <hi>ALSO OF JACOB</hi> BICKES her Brother of 7. yeares old. Aug. 6. 1664.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESAI.</hi> 65. 20.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The childe ſhall dye an hundred yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res old, bot the ſinner being an hundreth yeares old ſhalbe accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH.</hi> 21. 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Have ye never read. Out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings thou haſt perfyted praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUK.</hi> 18. 16, 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Jeſus called the litle children to him, and ſaid: Suffer little children to come unto me, for of ſuch is the Kingdome of God. Verilie I ſay unto you: who ſo receiveth not the Kingdome of God as a litle childe he ſhall in nowiſe enter therein.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:2"/>
            <head>READER.</head>
            <p>THis was done at firſt in another language And albeit I knowe that ther is ſoe much ſobriety in the moſt able, who put pen to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in thoſe dayes, as maketh them to find ſome ſcarring upon their owne ſpirits: when they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, how many of thoſe who look upon a new book, may happen to welcome it into the world, with a word of ſnuffing diſdaine, <hi>Tuſh, the world is too full of books already.</hi> Yet I am ſome what above the feare of the hardeſt cenſure for this ſmall and indirect acceſſion to the adding of one poor ſheet more; that I am rather confident that (Read who will theſe few pages) his conſcience within him (ſuch as it is) will extort ſo much from him, like a teſtimony to the wayes of God that he ſhall at leaſt ſay, <hi>O that I may dye the death of the righteous, and that my latter end might be as his.</hi> And that the Reader, who is taught the feare of the Lord, wilbe farther enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened and refreſhed, and perſwaded of the wayes of holines. And more particularly of theſe few things following. Firſt, that ther is a <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> which dwelleth in, and ſhalbe with the ſaints for ever. And 2. that he is <hi>the comforter</hi> who alone can and ſhould comfort the ſoule. And 3. that his conſolations are not ſmall; by which ther is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for joy of heart and glorifieing God even in the fires, and by which beleivers are enabled to laugh at deſtruction and famine, and dearth and peſtilence, and to lift up their heads, and be able to ſtand before the Sonne of God, though they ſhould live to ſee the greateſt diſtreſſes of nations, and the ſhakeings of heaven and earth: which
<pb facs="tcp:37256:3"/> make the hearts of the ſtoute to ſtoope, and faile. 4. That the pure ordinances of Chriſt are noe vayn things but ought to be much followed and cleaved unto, and that there Chriſt giveth <hi>his loves.</hi> 5. That the word is that ſword of the Spirit, and ther is none like it againſt that <hi>Goliah,</hi> that red Dragon, that Leviathan, and the King of Terrors. How mighty was this young Damſell in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and the young one wanted not his own number of Scripture places: by which, through gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, they did quit themſelves like men, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came: and, at their death, declared themſelves, by the faith and conſolation of the Scripturs, to have attained to the ſtature of perfect men. Chriſtians, know what houre it is of your day, and what is your work. Be faithfull in the leſſer or greater things of opportunity and means of working out your ſalvation. You do not know what evill may be upon the earth; albeit we know, that the Cup of trembling (go round as it will) from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Nation, from Church to Church, from Citie to Citie, from Family to Family: yea, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, it beginneth at the houſe of God, and his own ſanctuary. Ezek. 9. 2 Pet. 3. But yet a little whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, and it ſhalbe taken out of the hand of the Lords people, and the dregs therof ſhalbe wrung out by all the wicked of the earth, and that moſt Signally, by Antichriſt, apoſtates, ſeducers, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters, and others alſo, who have a forme of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and deny the power therof.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:3"/>
            <head>THE LAST HOURES OF SUSANNA BICKES in the 14<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h yeare of her age.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>USANNA BICKES</hi> borne in Leyden Ianuarij 24. 1650. was viſited / from the hand of the Lord / with the Peſtilence / upon the 30. of Auguſt 1664. being Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnday / betuixt 7. of 8. at night. And after the beginning of her ſickneſſe / there were conſiderable preſages of her death. And very ſpeedily ſhe betooke herſelf to the great Phyſician of ſoule and body. The firſt night / ſhe exerciſed herſelf to earneſt prayer / by herſelf alone (without many words / or ſpeech to others) that God would furniſh her with ſtrength in her ſoule / to beare out that great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict / which ſhe did apprehend to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching with the waves of death: that ſhe might by faith and patience / as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh a dyeing Chriſtian / pertake of the victorie / which Chriſt hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over death / to all theſe / for whom he himſelfe had taſted of death. And as God had bleſt the preaching of the word abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to her / and the exerciſes privat and publict / upon the Cathechiſme: So / that ſhe had acquired a mervellous mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge / and daily increaſing
<pb facs="tcp:37256:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the ſame / from the very day that ſhe was in any capacity to learne: So / what inſtruction ſhe received in the grounds of Religion: it did ſoe take hold upon her / that not only ſhe retayned the notions therof in her underſtanding: Bot the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the trueth wer engraven upon her heart / of which ſhe gave remarkable proofes at this tyme of her death. And that the word of God had dwelt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in her: wherby ſhe was enabled to ſpeak unto herſelfe / and to ſing with grace in her heart / making ſweet medoly to the Lord / while ſurrounded with the billowes of the King of Terrors / marching in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell array againſt her / with the terrible ſlaughter weapon of the Peſtilence. As abundanly is evident by the enſueing words uttered by her / and faithfully collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and / by the advyce and help of ſome iudicious and Religious perſons / publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed / for the uſe of others both old and young. The accompt whereof might have been much larger then heer it is done; but that ſeverall things did eſcape the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the byſtanders / and of the Penman / being partlie through grief / and partlie through wonder / diverted from the exact noteing of the things which ſhe uttered.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of her ſickneſs / ſhe was heard / with much feeling and power / breaking foorth to God with theſe words of <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 119. <hi>If thy law wer not my delyt I ſhould periſh in my affliction.</hi> Wherupon
<pb facs="tcp:37256:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> her Father ſaid to her: be of good comfort my child / the Lord wilbe neer unto thee / and us / under this heavie and ſore tryel / and will not forſake us; although now he chaſten us. David / by theſe words / belike / meant of the Lords hand which had been heavie both upon his houſe and upon his perſon ſeverall wayes. Wherof we read in the Scripture. Yea Father / ſaid ſhe / <hi>Our heavenlie Father doth chaſten us for our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that we may partake of his holineſſe.</hi> As we read <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 10, 11. And albeit (as it is ſaid there) <hi>no chaſtening for the preſent time ſeemeth to be joyeous bot greivous: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, afterwards, it yeeldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſſe unto them who are exerciſed by it.</hi> The Lord is now chaſtening me upon this ſick-bed / and I hope he will bleſſe it ſoe / as to make it to yeeld unto me that ſame bleſſed fruit / according to the riches of his mercy and compaſſions which faile not: and then ſighing to God with her eyes up to heaven / ſhe ſaid: be mercifull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me / o Father / be mercifull unto me poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſinner according to thy word.</p>
            <p>And looking upon her ſorrowing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents who ſtood by her. Father ſaid ſhe / It is ſaid in the 55. <hi>Pſal. vers</hi> 23. <hi>Caſt thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den upon the Lord: and he ſhall ſuſtaine thee: for he will never ſuffer the righteous to be moved.</hi> Therefore / dear Father and Mother / caſt all your care and ſorrow upon the Lord who ſhall make all things goe well that concerne you. Oh (ſaid the Mother) my
<pb facs="tcp:37256:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> deare child / I have had noe ſmall comfort from the Lord in thee / and the fruits of his grace in thee / wherby thow haſt been ſo much exerciſed unto godlineſſe in the word / and prayer / and religious and gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours unto thine owne and our comfort and edification. The Lord himſelfe / who gave us thee / make up our loſs of thee: If it be his pleaſure that we muſt now parte one from another. D. Mother (ſaid ſhe) albeit I leave yow / yet God ſhall never forſake yow: for it is ſaid <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. 15, 16. <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the fruit of her wombe: yea ſhe may forget: yet I wil not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thee. Behold I have graven thee upon the palms of my hand &amp;c.</hi> Oh comfortable words both for mothers and children. Mark dear Mother / how faſt the Lord keepeth and holdeth his people that he hath them (even) graven on the palmes of his hand. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think with your ſelf / that albeit I muſt parte with yow or ye with mee / yet the Lord ſhall never ſeparat from you or me.</p>
            <p>She being wearied through much ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king / deſired to reſt a little : and after a verie little tym ſhe awaked. Her Father aſked how it was with her / but ſhe aſked what day of the week it is now. Her Father told her / it was the Lords day. Well ſaid ſhe / have ye given up my name to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered in the publict prayers. Her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther told her he had done ſoe. I have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / ſaid ſhe / that <hi>the effectuall fervent prayer</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37256:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>of the Righteous doth availe much.</hi> The two worthie Miniſters / who are aftermentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / ſhe wold have much deſired they ſhould have been by her / but from her love to them / being much tender and carefull of their ſafetie / ſhe wold not have them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to viſite her: but rather ſatisfied her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be caſt upon the Lords owne hand / and to accept of / and improve the viſits of others / whom the providence of God ſhould ſend unto her: or thoſe (who being judged by the Church ſitt for the viſiting of the ſick in theſe caices of hazard) are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wont to come with more freedom. Of whom their was one who uſed to come ſeverall tymes to her / and who was through the Lords bleſſing uſefull to her: to whom ſhe gave heartie thanks for his viſit. And one tym / after he was gone / ſhe began to weep bitterlie / and her Father aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked her the cauſe. Have I not matter for weeping / ſaid ſhe / for what I have heard / but juſt now / by the viſiter: that <hi>Domine de Witte</hi> was to day taken ſick in the pulpit / and went home ſo unwell. which is a ſadd token for the people. For / when God is about to ſmyte a Land or a Citie / often ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes he ſmyteth and removeth their Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / and ought we not then to lay ſuch a thing to heart. altho for my part / I know that I ſhall not long live to behold the evill which may come / and which I have helped to procure als well as others. And therefore I pray with <hi>David</hi> Pſa. 25. <hi>Remember not,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37256:6"/> 
               <hi>O Lord the ſinnes of my youth, nor my treſpaſſes, according to thy tender mercie, remember thou me for thy goodnes ſake, O Lord.</hi> Oh how do I long; even <hi>as the Hart panteth after the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brooks, ſo panteth my thirſtie ſoule after thee, O God. My ſoule thirſteth for God, the living God.</hi> Oh how doth my ſoule thirſt all the day <hi>after thee, O God.</hi> Pſa. 42. And farther / in the words of that 51. Pſal. <hi>Have mercy upon me, O Lord, according to thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; according to the multitud of thy tender mercies, blot out my tranſgreſſions.</hi> And ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the 11. vers / which ſhe much inſiſted upon / often repeating the ſame / eſpecially the 5. vers / <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in iniquitie, and in ſinne did my mother conceive me.</hi> Vpon which words ſhe enlarged her medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and ſpeech / according as ſhe had learned from the Scriptures and the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme / and the books written thereupon for explication / concerning that ſubject of originall ſinne. This is comed / ſaid ſhe from the diſobedience and fall of our firſt parents in paradiſe / that our nature is ſoe corrupted; that we are all / &amp; altogider con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and borne in ſinne: So we read alſo Gen. 5. 3. Thus / <hi>Adam</hi> (it is ſaid) <hi>begat a ſonn after his owne likneſſe.</hi> Sinne is not of God / for <hi>he hath formed man upright in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining; but he hath ſought out many inventions.</hi> Eccl. 7. 29. <hi>Therefore, as by one man ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſoe death paſſed upon all men, for that all have ſinned: but death reigned from Adam to Moſes; even over</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37256:6"/> 
               <hi>them who had not ſinned after the ſimilitude of Adams tranſgreſſion.</hi> Rom. 5.</p>
            <p>She ſpoke alſo many things verie judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlie of the old man / and the putting off the ſame: and of the new man / and of the putting on thereof: from Eph. 4. and then ſhe fell again upon the 51. Pſa. and theſe words / <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a broken heart, a broken and a contrite Spirit, O Lord, thow wilt not deſpiſe?</hi> that brokenneſſe of heart / ſaid ſhe / which is built upon / and / floweth from faith: and that faith which is built upon Chriſt / who is the propper and alone true ſacrifice for ſinne. And heerupon ſhe ſpoke of the offerings and ſacrifices of <hi>Abel</hi> and of <hi>Cain.</hi> Hebr. 11. 4.</p>
            <p>Thereafter ſhe deſired to reſt and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing ſlumbered a little / ſhe ſaid / ah dear F. and M. How weake doe I find my ſelfe. My dear child / ſaid her Father / God ſhall in his tender mercy ſtrengthen you in your weakeneſſe. Yea Father / ſaid ſhe / that is my confidence / for it is ſaid Iſai. 42. <hi>The bruiſed reed he will not break, and the ſmoaking flax he will not quench.</hi> Should I not then believe / read Hebr. 11. <hi>How Abraham being proved of God did by faith offer up Iſaac in ſacrifice.</hi> Oh what a ſtedfaſt &amp; loyall faith was that of Abraham / which made him willing and readie to offer that his owne one ſonne. Oh / what is faith? <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, &amp; the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> Heb. 11. 1. Alſo 2. Tim. 2. 19. <hi>the fundation of God ſtandeth ſure, haveing this ſeale, The Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37256:7"/> thoſe who are his owne.</hi> Bot now dear F. and M. why weep ye ſoe over me / kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weing ſoe well / I hope / that if the Lord ſhalbe pleaſed to take me out of this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wofull world / it ſhalbe well with me / and that therwith ye ought to be content. It is ſaid Pſal. 115. <hi>Our God is in the heavens and doth all what ſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> Yea / we pray every day that his will may be done on earth as it is done in heaven. Now Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / this is Gods will / that I ly upon this ſick-bed of this diſeas. Therefore we muſt be content that it be to us according to our prayer. Otherwis we then ſhould murmure againſt God: without whoſe good pleaſure / nothing comes to pas. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I be thus ſtricken with ſo heavy and ſadd a diſeas: yet it is the will of God / and ther is my ſilence. Therfore I will pray that his will be done and not mijne. Therfore / Father / never doubt of Gods providence / for it is ſaid Matth. 10. <hi>are not two ſparrowes ſold for a ferthing and that not one of them falleth to the earth without your Father, yea the haires of your head are alſo numbred.</hi> Therefore <hi>fear not: ye are better then many ſparrowes.</hi> And Lam. 3. 38. <hi>There goeth not out of the mouth of the almightie good and evill.</hi> Adverſity and proſperitie are both good. Some things may ſeem evill in our eyes / but the Lord turneth all to good. Amos 3. 6 <hi>Shall ther be evill in the city which the Lord doth not.</hi> Cometh not the Peſtilence from God. What mean thoſe people / who ſay that it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37256:7"/> cometh by the air? and is not the Lord the Creator and the Ruler of the air / and all the Elements. Or / if it come out of the earth: yet is it of the Lord. What talke they; that it came which a ſhip which was come from Africa. We have long agoe read together out of Lev. 26. 25. <hi>I ſhall bring a ſword upon you to avenge the quarrel of my covenant, &amp; where you are aſſembled in your cities, then ſhall I bring the peſtilence in the midſt of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this / ſhe ſought ſome reſt again: and having ſlumbred a little / ſhe ſaid / O now my dear Fat. and Mot. now is this day for the opening of the firſt queſt. of the catechiſme / and if we were there with others; we ſhould heare / that whether in death / or life; we are the Lord I. Chriſts / our faithfull Saviour / who hath by his owne precious blood re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us from the power of the divel. And the following words / Rom. 14. 8. <hi>for none of us liveth to himſelf, &amp; none of us dyeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for whether we live: we live unto the Lord, and whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord, whether then we live, or dye, we are the Lords.</hi> Then be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted: for whether I dye / I ſhall dye to the Lord / or if I live I ſhall live to the Lord. The life which God at firſt gave me; I have as yet / and ſo long as the ſoule is in the body there is hope. wherfore then doe ye ſo much afflict yourſelves. But what ſhall I ſay: with weeping I came into ye world, and with weeping muſt I goe out of it. Oh my deare parents / <hi>better is the day of death then the day of ones birth.</hi> Eccleſ. 7. 1. <hi>Ther is a</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37256:8"/> 
               <hi>time to be borne, and a time to dye.</hi> If my time to dye / be not comed, I ſhall then not dye. So then ye muſt comfort yourſelves / and thinke that God ſhall make all well. Ah my d. F. and M. let us pray together / and pray the Lord with me; that he would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe upon me a quiet and peaceable paſſage through death. Her Father / after he had prayed. being full of fatherlie ſympathie and care of ſuch a childe; both in what concerned her ſoul and bodie / aſked her / if he ſhould once more bring the phyſician to her. Nay / ſaid ſhe / the Doctor ſhall doe me nothing / nor can he help me / but I hope abundantly that my heavenly Father ſhall help me. Well / ſaid her Father / my child we ſhall uſe the ordinary meanes: and let the Lord bleſſe / as he ſees good. Yea / ſaid ſhe / deare Father / the heavenly Phyſican is the true helper: he ſhall help / he can help both ſoul and body. It is ſaid Matth. 11. 28. <hi>Come unto me all ye who are weary, &amp; heavie loaden and I will give you reſt.</hi> See there / Father / there is the helper / even as Pſa. 50. call upon me in the day of diſtreſs: I ſhall delyver / and thou ſhalt glorifie me. All who are in trouble / muſt call upon God alone / for when humain helpe is done: then beginneth Gods helpe for them who call upon him in trueth and in faith. Therfore let us once more pray. After her Father had prayed / the friend above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned came to viſit her / and as the Lord had ſo opened and enlarged her heart that every word ſpoken to her from the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37256:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Scriptur tooke hold upon her with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing impreſſion / ſo was the viſiter alſo much refreſhed by her / wondering at the grace of God in her / and that ſhe ſpake ſo pertinently and aftectionatly to her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents / for comforting them. And ſo after ſhe had bid him thanks for his viſit / he took his leave with tears: which were tears als much of joy as ſorrow. When he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / ſhe aſked what day is it now / they told her / it was Monday. Then ſaid ſhe / to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is the catechiſing day in our quarter. Ther is one thing I will earneſtly beg of you / Father / and that ye will promiſe it to me / and that is; that ye ſhall goe to <hi>Dom. de Witte</hi> and <hi>Ardinois,</hi> and thanke them for the learning and inſtruction which I reaped by their catechiſing / and tell them that theſe excellent and brave places of Scripture which they taught me upon the catechiſme at the meetings in the Kirk / have been / and are bleſſed of God for my comfort / now upon my death bed / yea / are uſefull unto me / for my ſalvation. Oh that ſweet catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: unto which I did alwis reſort with gladnes / and waited upon it without wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieing / untill it was ended. I have ſeen and underſtood / that there is ſo little comfort and good / &amp; ſo much vanity in the Kermis &amp; holy idle dayes of play / that I have grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved / and been aſhamed both for young and old people / to ſee them ſo glad and mad upon vanity. Alſo dear Father ye ſhall give thanks to my Schoolmaſter / and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37256:9"/> Miſtreſſe; who taught me the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of my reading / I intreat and hope that ye will doe ſo / and not forget my thanks to the Miniſters / as ye have already promiſed. Yea / ſaid her Father / I promiſe you I ſhall / if the Lord preſerve my life and health (which accordingly he did / at convenient occaſion / on her behalfe: which was refreſhing / &amp; acceptable to theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men / as if it had been a preſent of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature / from ſome greater perſonage.</p>
            <p>Being wearied and weakened with ſpeaking / ſhe ſought ſome reſt; and haveing turned her to the wall / ſhe ſlumbered about a quarter of an houre / and being awake / her Father aſked how ſhe did / and expreſt ſomewhat of the great ſatiſfaction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment he had in her reading / and wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting / and her religious profiting. Yea Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / ſaid ſhe: in that ye hav been ſo carefull for me / to get me to read and learne / hath been better to me / then if ye had provyded ten thouſand gilders of portion for me: for therby have I learned to comfort myſelfe out of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Her Father perceiving her groweing weake / ſaid to her / my dear child / I think thou becomes very weake. Yea ſaid ſhe / I feel it ſo more and more / as alſo your grief for me / I ſee / doth increaſe / which is a pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of my affliction. be content I pray you / it is the Lord who doth all this. And let us (with <hi>David</hi> 2 Sam. 24. 14.) fall in <hi>the Lords hand; for his mercies are great. David,</hi> while his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37256:9"/> childe was ſick / he faſted / and ate not: but when the childe was dead / and God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his purpoſe in it; then he did eat. Yea / why ſhould I now faſt / ſaid he? <hi>can I bring him back from death: I ſhall goe to him, but he ſhall not returne to me.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 23. ſo ought ye to comfort yourſelf alſo / after my death / and ſay / our childe is wel; for we know that they who truſted in God / are well. My dear Mother / who hath done ſo much for me / ye muſt promiſe to me / that after my death ye ſhall not ſorrow ſo much: for I am afraid for you / when I conſider your grief for me / and for my other ſiſter / and brother / who are gone through death before me. And conſider your neighbor / who hath loſt her two ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / &amp; hath no more children. Ye ſhall both of you promis me / that yee will comfort one another. Comfort yourſelves with <hi>Job, who haveing loſt all his children, ſaid, the Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away: bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Doe ye not think but it went very ſadd with him. Ye know well that Chriſt ſaid to the Apoſtles <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 33. <hi>In the world ye ſhall have tribulation. But be of good comfort: in me ye ſhall have peace: I have overcome the world.</hi> And muſt the Apoſtles ſuffer ſo great tribulations? and ſhall not we endure ſome what. Yea / hath not Ieſus Chriſt my only life and favior / in the garden of Bethſemane / ſwatt blood for my ſake. was he not mocked / and ſpitted upon in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem: and / therafter / nailed unto the croſſ: and a ſpeare thruſt through his bleſſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37256:10"/> ſide: and all this for my ſake; for my ſtinking ſinnes ſake. Yea <hi>there he cried with a loud voice: my God, my God, wherefore haſt thou forſaken me. Now thus hath he purchaſed his church with his own blood. Act.</hi> 20. 28. From the croſs is that precious blood to be gotten / <hi>which alone can cleanſe us from all ſinne.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 7. There did Ieſus hang naked / who hath purchaſed to me the garment of ſalvation / <hi>and clothed me with the rob of righteouſnes. Iſai</hi> 6. 10. And ſalvation is in none other beſides him. Yea <hi>there is no other name in heaven, or earth among men, by which to be ſaved. Act.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
            <p>Oh deare F. and M. I waxe more and more feeble / and weake. oh / that I may quyetly fall aſleep in his boſome: and till then / he may ſtrengthen me / and take me in his armes / as he did the litle children / and ſaid Mark. 10. 14. <hi>ſuffer little children to come unto me, for of ſuch is the kingdome of God.</hi> And it is ſaid <hi>vers</hi> 16. <hi>he took them in his armes, and laid his hands upon them, and bleſſed them.</hi> I lye heer as a childe. o Lord / I am a childe; receiv me into thy gratious armes. o Lord / grace / grace / and not juſtice / for if thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in judgement with me I can not ſtand. <hi>Yea no living ſhall in thy ſight be juſtified. Pſal.</hi> 143. 2. <hi>for there is none who ſinneth not.</hi> 1. <hi>k.</hi> 8. 4. 6.</p>
            <p>Thus with continued ſpeaking ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very faint / and all her ſtrength ſeemed quite gone; yet ſhe forced a cry more / ah my dear mother / ah how faint and feeble. This did ſo pierce the heart of her mother;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37256:10"/> that ſhe could ſay nothing / but ah my dear child. Then began ſhe again to comfort her mother: ſo long as my life is in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / there is hope / ſaid ſhe. If it ſhould pleas the Lord to recover me to life and health: how carefull / and earneſt would I be to pleas you / in my work / and learning / and what ye would require / and lay upon me. And here upon again being a litle more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived / the Lord renued her ſtrength won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully / to ſpeak as before / and to comfort herſelfe / and her parents / out of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / ſayeing with the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28. <hi>we know that all things work together for good to thoſe who love God; even to theſe who are the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God, according to his purpoſe.</hi> O God / eſtabliſh me with thy free ſpirit: that I never fall from thy love. Yea / its ſaid there / <hi>who ſhall ſeparat us from the love of Chriſt. I am perſwaded that neither life, nor death, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor deepth, nor any other creature, ſhall ſeparat us from the love of God; which is toward us in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Alſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 27, 28, 29. <hi>My ſheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternall life, and they ſhall never periſh, and no man ſhall plucke them out of my hand. my Father, who gave them me, is greater then all, and none ſhall pull them out of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hand.</hi> But now let me reſt a litle.</p>
            <p>After ſome ſlumbering / ſhe ſpake to her Father again / with much gladnes / and joy of heart. It is ſaid / ſayth ſhe 1. <hi>Cor,</hi> 15.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37256:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 54, 55, 56, 57. <hi>death is ſwallowed up of victorie: o death where is thy ſting; o Hell? where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, the ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinn is the law: but God be thanked who giveth us victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> There ey / ſee that my dear ſavior hath overcome death? and the ſting of death? who then would not be earneſtly content to dye. For we muſt all once dye. We are from the earth / and to the earth we muſt returne / the duſt is mother of us all. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>the duſt ſhall tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to duſt, from whence it is, and the ſpirit to God, who gave it.</hi> So that my ſpirit ſhall turne to God / who is the giver of all things. But oh / what is mans life upon earth. <hi>The dayes of man upon earth are as the graſs, as the flowre of the field, ſo he flooriſheth. The wind paſſeth over it, and it is no more. And his place knoweth him no more. Pſal.</hi> 103. 15, 16. And if a man ſhould live long; yet the longer he ſhould live / he ſhould the more have ſinn. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 10. <hi>The dayes of our yeares are threeſcore and ten yeares. And if by ſtrength, they be fourſcore: yet is the ſtrength therof labor and ſorrow.</hi> Now the Lord ſhall free me from all that labor / and that ſorrow. Suppoſe / and think with yourſelves / that ye were both ſick / and the Lord ſhould come and take you from us / and leave us poore children behind you? How farr greater loſs ſhould that ſeem for us. Is it not better that the Lord remove us firſt / who would / belike / have ſo few freinds behind you. Bot we know not the thoughts of the Lord: yet we know / 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37256:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> they are peace and good / and not evill / and to give an expected end / unto good. But oh? what ſhall I ſay; my life ſhall not continue long / I feel ſo much anxiety. Oh / Lord / look upon me graciouſly: have pitty upon my weake and diſtreſſed heart / my diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule: I am oppreſt / undertake for me / that I may ſtand faſt and overcome. Heer again / a little reviving / ſhe ſaid.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid / <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 16. <hi>I wil pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter, who ſhall remain with you for ever, even the ſpirit of trueth.</hi> O Lord let him not leave me. O Lord continue with me / till my battell and work be finiſhed. Without thee I can doe nothing. Ioh. 15. 5. <hi>I am,</hi> ſaid Chriſt / <hi>the true vine, and my Father is the huſband-man.</hi> ah / ah / my God let me be a branch of that living vine. Oh / what are we poor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes / who can of ourſelves do nothing. O dear Father / how lame / and halting goe we in the wayes of God and ſalvation. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9, 10. <hi>For we know but in part, and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie but in part, but when that which is perfect is come: then ſhall that which is in part be done away.</hi> Oh that I had attayned to that. Now? but what are we of ourſelves. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5 ſee / not only / the weakenes / &amp; nothingnes / but alſo the wickedneſs of man: <hi>that all the imaginations of the thoughts of the heart are evill, and only evill continually.</hi> and <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>We were by nature the children of wrath,</hi> and are <hi>conceived and borne in ſinne, and unrighteouſnes. Pſal.</hi> 51. Oh / oh / this wretched and vile thing / ſinn.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37256:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> But thanks be to God who hath redeemed me from it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15, 16, 17. <hi>Ye have not received the ſpirit of bondage again to feare: but ye have received the ſpirit of adoption, by which ye crie Abba, Father. It is the ſpirit which witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with our ſpirit that we are the children of God. And if children, then are we heirs; Heirs of God, and joint heires with Chriſt.</hi> Thence ye ſee / Father / that I ſhalbe a fellow heir with Chriſt / who hath ſaid <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 2, 3. <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many manſions, I goe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a place for you. And if I goe to prepare a place for you, I will come againe, and take you to my ſelfe, that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</hi> O Lord take me to thy ſelfe. Behold / dear M. he hath prepared a place and dwelling for me. Yea / my dear child / ſaid her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhall ſtrengthen you / with his holy ſpririt / untill he hath fitted you / and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you fully for that place / which he hath prepared for you. Yea Mother / it is ſaid in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>How lovlie are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of hoſts: my ſoule doth thirſt, and longeth for the courts of the Lord: one day in thy courtes, is better then a thouſand.</hi> Yea / ſaid David / <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a doorekeeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in tents of the wicked.</hi> Read that Pſalm D. M. and therwith ye may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another. As for me / I am more and more ſpent / and draw neer to my laſt houre. Pray with me. Pray that the Lord would vouchſafe unto me a ſoft death. And when they had prayed with her / ſhe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her to her Mother / and with much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37256:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
/ ſhe ſaid / ah my dear and loving Mother / that which cometh from the heart / doth ordinarily goe to the heart. Once come and kiſs me before I leave you / and alſo my dear father / and my ſiſter. And / father / let my ſiſter be trained up in the wayes of God / as I have been / I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed and weeped for my ſiſter / thinking ſhe ſhould dye; and now ſhe weepeth for me. Alſo / ſhe took her young litle ſiſter in her armes / a child of 6. monethes old / and ſhe kiſſed it with much affection / as if her bowels had been moved: and ſpake with many heart-breaking words / both to the parents / and the children. Her father ſaid to one ſtanding by; Take from her that poore lambkin / from the hazard of that fierie ſickneſſe. Give her from you: for ye have too much already to beare. Well father / ſaid ſhe / did not God preſerv the 3 children in the fierie fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nace. Ye yourſelf learned me from Iſai 43. 3. <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this / ſhe had ſome litle reſt / and being awaked / ſhe ſaid. We read 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 42, 43. <hi>The body is ſown in corruption; but ſhalbe raiſed incorruptible. It is ſown in diſhonour, but ſhalbe raiſed in glory: it is ſown in weakneſs, but ſhalbe raiſed in power.</hi> Behold thus it is / and thus it ſhalbe with my poore mortal fleſh. Revel. 14. 13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead who dye in ye Lord, becaus they doe reſt from their</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37256:13"/> 
               <hi>labour, and their workes ſhall follow them: Iſai.</hi> 57. 1, 2. <hi>The righteous periſh, and no man layeth it to heart; and the upright are taken away, and no man regardeth it; that they are taken away before the evill which cometh. They ſhall enter into peace: they ſhall reſt in their beds, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one who have walked in their uprightneſſe.</hi> Behold now father / I ſhall reſt and ſleep in that bed-chamber. Alſo <hi>Job</hi> ſaith / <hi>chap.</hi> 19. 25, 26, 27. <hi>I know that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemet liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth. And though, after my skin, worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God. Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelfe, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another; though my reines be conſumed within me.</hi> Behold now / father / this very ſkin which ye ſee / and this very fleſh / which ye ſee / ſhalbe raiſed up again: and theſe very eyes / which now are ſo dim / ſhall on that day ſee and behold my dear and pretious Redeemer. Albeit the wormes ſhall eat up my fleſh; yet with theſe eyes ſhall I behold God: even I myſelf and not another for me. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 28, 22. <hi>Mervell not for this: for the houre is coming, in the which all who are in the grave, ſhall heare, and come foorth: theſe who have done good, unto the reſurrection of life.</hi> See / Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / I ſhall riſe on that day / and then I ſhall behold my Redeemer; then ſhall ſhe ſay / <hi>come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared fore you, before the beginning of the world.</hi> Behold / now <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me: and the life that I now</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:37256:13"/> 
               <hi>live in the fleſh, is by the Faith of the Sonne of God, who loved me, and hath given him ſelfe for me. I am ſaved, and that of grace, through faith: and that not of my ſelf: it is the gift of God. Not of workes: to the end that no man ſhould boaſt. Eph.</hi> 2, 8 9, My dear Parents / now we muſt ſhortlie parte: my ſpeech faileth me. pray the Lod for a quiet cloſe to my combat. All our dear childe / how ſad is that to us / that we muſt parte. Yea ſaid ſhe; I goe to heaven / and there ſhall we find one another. I goe to Ieſus Chriſt / and to my Brother Iacob / who did ſo much crie to God / and call upon him / to the very laſt breathing: and to my litle ſiſter / which was but three years of age / when it dyed: and when we aſked it? if it would dye: yea / ſaid it / if it be Gods will / I will goe to my litle brother if the Lord will. Or / I will alſo ſtay with my Mother / if it be his wil: but I know that I ſhall dye / and goe to heaven / to God. Oh / ſee how ſo ſmall a babe / to which ſo much grace was given / as to have it ſelf / every way / and in all things / ſo ſubjected / and ſubmitted to the will of God: as if it had no will of it's own / it ſaid alwiſe; <hi>If it be the will of God: if it pleas God:</hi> Nothing for it / but as it was <hi>the will of God? the pleaſure of God, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore / dear F. and M. give the Lord thanks for this his free / and rich grace: and then I ſhall the more gladlie be gone. Be gratious then O Lord unto me alſo / be gracious to me: <hi>waſh me throughlie from</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37256:14"/> 
               <hi>my unrighteouſhes, &amp; cleanſe me from my ſinne.</hi> It is ſaid <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Although your ſinnes were as skarlet, they ſhalbe white as ſnow. Although they were red as crimſon, yet they ſhalbe as wooll.</hi> Behold / God hath waſhen away my ſinn. Oh how doe I long: <hi>for in this body,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle / <hi>we earneſtlie ſigh, and groan, longing for our houſe which is in heaven; that we may be therewith cloathed.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2. Now I alſo ly heer ſighing / and longing for that dwelling / which is above. In the ſame ſermon / which I heard / or ſhall ever heare / on earth; I heard of this / in the new Kirk: which is matter of great comfort now unto me.</p>
            <p>Then ſhe brought foorth ſeverall notable ſcriptures / which were quoted in that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon / eſpecially. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. And then ſhe called for prayer. Pray with me / ſaid ſhe / that my ſins may be forgiven me / and that I may have the more abundant faith / and aſſureance of it / and the comfort of that aſſureance / and the ſtrength of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort / according to my neceſſity. She prayed herſelf / and continued a pretty ſpace.</p>
            <p>After prayer (in which ſhe inſiſted prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally / for pardon of ſinne) ſhe ſaid / my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> parents? have I angered / or grieved you / at any time: or done what became me not; forgive it me. O poor childe / ſay they / if all children caryed ſo to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents / as thou haſt done / there ſhould be leſſ grief and ſorrow / upon all hands. And if any ſuch thing had eſcaped thee / we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37256:14"/> would forgive it / with our wholl heart: you have done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a good childe.</p>
            <p>The heart of her being quieted by her peace with God her Father in the heavens / and her peace with her parents on Earth / then ſhe began to diſpone her books / and other litle things: and as the grace of God had made her ſo wiſe unto ſalvation; ſo ſhe did ſhowe ſome proportion of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian prudence / almoſt in every thing / ſmaller / and greater. My dear mother / ſaid ſhe / ye ſhall keep my Catechiſe book / in remembrance of me. Ye ſhall keep <hi>Dom. de Witts</hi> Catechiſation / ſo long as ye live: and let my litle ſiſter have the other book / as my remembrance. In the mean while / ſhe told that ſhe found her heart exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pained / and overwhelmed / and that ſhe knew that her life ſhould quicklie paſſe away. Her Father ſpeaking a word / as he was able / hoping the Lord would be neer with his ſtrength in this ſad hour of her neceſſity. Yea / ſaid ſhe / <hi>The Lord is my ſhepherd: Although I paſs through the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the valley of death; I will not feare, for thou art with me: thy rod and thy ſtaff ſhall comfort me Pſa.</hi> 23. And it is ſaid / <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>the ſufferings of this preſent life, are not worthy to be compared to the glory which ſhalbe revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in us.</hi> Shall I not ſuffer and endure: ſeing my glorious Redeemer behoved to ſuffer ſo much. Oh how was he mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed / and ſpitted on / and crowned with thornes / that he might parchaſe a crowne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37256:15"/> of righteouſneſs for us. And that is the crowne / of which Paul ſaid / 2. <hi>Theſ</hi> 4. 7, 8. <hi>I have foughten the good fight, I have finiſhed my race, and keeped the faith. Henceforth, is laid up for me, a crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, ſhall give unto me in that day: and not only to me, but to all who love his appearing.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. <hi>Ye are bought with a price: therefore glorifie God in your ſoules and bodyes, which are his.</hi> Muſt I not then exalt / and bleſs him / while I have being / who hath bought / yea bought me with his blood. <hi>Iſai</hi> 53. <hi>Surely he hath borne our griefes, &amp; took our infirmities: &amp; we eſteemed him ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſtricken of God. But he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, and bruiſed for our ſin: the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and through his ſtripes are we healed. And the Lord hath laid on him the iniquities of us all. Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſinn of the world.</hi> Behold / that Lamb is Ieſus Chriſt; alſo / for my ſinnes / he hath ſatisfied. So ſaid Paul 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Ye are waſhed, ye are ſanctified, ye are juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and through the Spirit of our God.</hi> My end is now very neer. Now ſhall I put on white raiment / and be cloathed before the Lamb / that ſpotleſſe Lamb / &amp; with his ſpotleſſe righteouſneſſe. Now are the Angels making ready to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie my ſoule before the throne of God. <hi>Thoſe are they who are come out of great tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, who have waſhed their robs, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. Revel.</hi> 7.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37256:15"/> She ſpoke this with a dying voice: but full of the Spirit / and of the power of faith. And this her lively aſſureance / and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of her ſalvation / ſhe further utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the words of Paul / 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1, 2. <hi>For we know, that if this earthlie houſe of our tabernacle, be diſſolved; we have one, which is built of God, a houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heaven. For in this we ſigh for our houſe, which is in heaven, that we may be cloathed therewith.</hi> There / Father / ye ſee that my body is this tabernacle / which now ſhall be broken downe. My ſoule ſhall now parte from it / and ſhall be taken up into heavenly Paradiſe / into that heavenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. There ſhali I dwell / and goe no more out; but ſitt and ſing / <hi>holy, holy, holy is the Lord God of hoſts, the Lord of ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth.</hi> And her laſt words; <hi>O Lord God, into thy hands I commit my Spirit.</hi> O Lord be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious / be mercifull unto me a poor ſinner; and heerupon ſhe fell aſleep. Being the 1 of September in the evening betwxt 7 and 8: haveing obtained / very remarkablie / that which / ſo often / ſhe intreated of the Lord: to wit / a ſoft and quiet departure / and the end of her faith / the ſalvation of her ſoule.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37256:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The laſt words of her Heer follow the laſt words of her BROTHER JACOB a childe of</hi> 7 <hi>yeares old.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis litle childe was viſited by the Lord with a very ſore ſicknes / upon the 6 of Auguſt: three or 4 weeks before his ſiſter / of whoſe death we have given ſome account already. For moſt part he ſleeped till neer his death. That which he ſpake ordinarlie / when he was awake; is / in theſe few words fowowing / com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the chriſtian Reader. So often as he awaked / he gave himſelf to pray. Once / when his parents had prayed / they aſked him? if they ſhould not / once more / call for the phyſician. Nay ſaid her, dear Fa. and Mo. I will not have the Doctor any more: The Lord ſhall help me. I know he ſhall take me to himſelf / and then he ſhall help all. Ah my dear child / ſaid the Father / that maketh my heart ſore. Well / ſaid the childe / Father / let us pray; and the Lord ſhall be neer / for my helper. And as the parents had again prayed / he ſaid / come now dear Fa. and Mo. and kiſs me. I know now / that I ſhall dye. Adew dear Fa. and Mo. adew my dear ſiſter: adew all. Now ſhall I goe to heaven unto God / and Ieſus
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37256:16"/> Chriſt / and the holy Angels. Father / know ye not what is ſaid / by <hi>Jeremie chap.</hi> 17. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he who truſteth in the Lord.</hi> Now I ſhall truſt in him / and he will bleſs me. And 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>Litle children, love not the world; for the world paſſeth away.</hi> away then all that is the world: away with all my pleaſant things in the world. away with my dager <hi>(which a Student had propined him)</hi> for where I goe / there is nothing to doe with dager / and ſword. Men ſhall not fight there / but praiſe God. Away with all my books / for where I goe / there is nothing adoe with books: There I ſhall know and be learned / ſufficiently / all things of true wiſdom / and learning / without books. The Father being aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with wonder / knew not well what to ſay; but / my dear childe / the Lord wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be neer to thee / and uphold thee. Yea / Father / ſaid he / the Apoſtle Peter ſaith. <hi>God reſiſteth the proud but he giveth grace unto the humble.</hi> I ſhall humble myſelf under the mightie hand of God; and he ſhall help / and lift me up. Ah my dear childe / ſaid the Father / haſt thou ſo ſtrong a faith. God will ſtrengthen thy ſaith. Yea ſaid the childe / Father / God hath given me ſo ſtrong a faith upon himſelf / through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; that the Divel himſelf ſhall flee from me: for it is ſaid <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>He who beleiveth on the ſonne, hath everlaſting life, And hath overcome the wicked one.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. Now I believe in Ieſus Chriſt my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37256:17"/>
/ and he will not leave nor forſake me. but ſhall give unto me eternall life. Then ſhall I ſing <hi>holy, holy, holy is the Lord of Sabaoth.</hi> And with the ſhort word of prayer <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a poore ſinner.</hi> He quietly breathed it out / and ſleept in the Lord. Auguſt 8. 1664.</p>
            <p>To conclude; we may ſee heer / by the mouth of theſe children <hi>(being, as it were, two or three of that bleſſed</hi> cloude of witneſſes. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 1.) That verified / which we read / <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 20. <hi>THE CHILDE SHALL DIE AN HUNDRED YEARES OLD.</hi> Reader I have noe more to ſay to thee; but / as thou would wiſh to live for ever / ſtand in alw of that which followeth / immediatlie / in that ſame vers: <hi>BUT THE SINNER</hi> / though <hi>AN HUNDRED YEARES OLD, SHALL BE ACCURSED.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37256:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
